Samuel George Morton Papers 1819-1850 Mss.B.M843
American Philosophical Society
Samuel George Morton Papers
1819-1850
Mss.B.M843
American Philosophical Society
2.25 Linear feet 5 boxes, bound volumes, microfilm
Through his craniometic studies of human races, the Philadelphia physician Samuel George Morton (1799-1851) exerted a profound influence on the development of physical anthropology in antebellum America, and made substantial contributions to mineralogy, paleontology, and natural history. Relating primarily to Morton's scientific interests, the Morton Papers include insights into Morton's perspectives on education, medical practice, geology and mineralogy, craniology, paleontology, the Wilkes Exploring Expedition (also known as the United States Exploring Expedition 1838-1842), and his two major monographs, the Crania Americana and Crania Aegyptiaca. Several of the letters were written by Morton in his capacity as corresponding secretary of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia. Also included in this collection are Morton's "Some Remarks on the Infrequency of Mixed Offspring Between the European and Australian Races" (1850), Joseph Barclay Pentland's notes on the aborigines of Peru (ca. 1840?), and newspaper clippings on Morton's death; a diary of Morton's trip to the West Indies, 1834, a set of craniological sketches for use in Crania Americana, and a microfilm of letters in private hands, written to Morton, 1838-1844
Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851
Bibliography
All of Morton's major published works are available at the APS, including:
Morton, Samuel George, Crania Aegyptiaca; or, Observations of Egyptian Ethnography Derived From Anatomy, History, and the Monuments (Philadelphia: J. Pennington, 1844). Call no.: 573.7 M84
Morton, Samuel George, Crania Americana: or, Comparative view of the skulls of various aboriginal nations of North & South America (Philadelphia: Dobson, 1839). Call no.: 573.7 M84c
African American History Note
Morton's diary, made on a trip that be made to the West Indies, records observations made on many of the Islands on life, work, agriculture, slavery, and derogatory comments on the native inhabitants.
Early American History Note
The Samuel George Morton Collection provides a window into the life of this nineteenth century scientist, explorer, and natural historian. The collection holds a wide-range of materials, and the correspondence touches on many different subjects. The entry in MOLE contains an item level accounting of the collection and its contents. The collection begins in the 1820s, when Morton is just beginning his career and continues through to the 1840s. Letters touch on topics, such as the treatment of Native Americans, Indian burial grounds, discoveries of fossilized remains, and medical education. Material on the Wilkes Expedition and especially on Morton’s early medical career is covered in depth. One letter contains a request from General Lafayette for a skull of an Indian for his own scientific collection. Most of the letters are to Morton and contain results of experiments or observations from travel and exploration. Additionally, the Diary to the West Indies form 1834 offers insight into the culture of the islands. Morton’s own involvement in the scientific racism is prominent in much of his later writing. Included in the collection are sketches of his “craniometrical drawings,” which were used by pro-slavery advocates.
Related Archival Materials note
The Library Company of Philadelphia owns the other major collection of Morton Papers, focussing generally on the later period in Morton's career and more intensively on Morton's craniology. The collection is served through the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.
Sixteen letters of Morton's with Victor and John James Audubon, 1836-1840, are located in the Archives of American Art at the Smithsonian Institution.
Morton appears as a correspondent in numerous other collections at the APS, including the Letters of Scientists Collection and the papers of William Maclure, John Edward Gray, John Fries Frazer, and William Parker Foulke.
Separated Materials note
Materials separated from the main body of the collection, with call numbers and location information as appropriate.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Series II has been microfilmed (film 1374).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Arthur V. Morton and Mrs. John Story Jenks, 1943. Series IV was filmed in 1980 from originals owned by Dr. Charles H. Montgomery (as of 2002).
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Samuel George Morton offer important insight into the development of the "American School" of physical anthropology during the infancy of the science, and insight into the conduct of natural history during its heyday in the 1830s.
Series I Correspondence, 1819-1850 1.5 linear feet
Series II Diary, 1833-ca.1837 1 vol. (25p.)
Series III Craniological sketches, ca.1838 11 items
Series IV Microfilm, 1838-1844 1 reel
Biographical/Historical note
Samuel George Morton (1799-1851, APS 1828) was a physician, anatomy professor, naturalist and physical anthropologist. Morton’s most important medical works include an American edition of John Mackintosh’s respected Principles of Pathology and Practice of Physic, and An Illustrated System of Human Anatomy. His Synopsis of the Organic Remains of the Cretaceous Group of the U.S. was a groundbreaking work in paleontology. But, his Crania Americana established Morton as Antebellum America's foremost craniologist, casting a long shadow over the history of physical anthropology and "race science."
Morton was the son of the Philadelphia merchant, George Morton, and Jane Cummings. He was left fatherless at an early age, and was taken by his mother to be raised in Westchester County, N.Y.. Attending Quaker schools, he was fed a steady diet of natural history and empirical science. He returned to Philadelphia in 1812 after his mother's remarriage to Thomas Rogers, an amateur mineralogist, who encouraged the boy’s early interest in science. Morton’s Quaker education continued first at the Westtown School in Pennsylvania, then at the Friend’s School in Burlington, N.J., headed by a family friend, astronomer and mathematician John Gummere (1784-1845, APS 1814).
In 1815, however, Morton's education was interrupted when he was apprenticed to a merchant in the city. After his mother's death in 1817, Morton broke away from commerce and began to study medicine with the prominent physician Joseph Parrish (1779-1840, APS 1815) at the University of Pennsylvania. He was awarded an M.D. degree in 1820. Support from a wealthy uncle in Ireland allowed Morton to further his medical education at the University of Edinburgh. While at Edinburgh University he also attended the geology lectures of Profesor Robert Jameson, who later taught the young Charles Darwin. Morton graduated from Edinburgh in 1823 with a thesis entitled De corporis dolore.
Morton returned to Philadelphia with sterling credentials as a physician; however, for several years, he struggled to establish himself in the city's tightly-knit medical community. In 1827 he married Rebecca Pearsall of Philadelphia, and they had eight children. Morton built up his practice slowly, becoming a physician to the Philadelphia Almshouse in 1829 and teaching in Joseph Parrish’s Philadelphia Medical Association for Medical Instruction after 1830. From 1839-1843 he served as Professor of Anatomy at Pennsylvania College (later Gettysburg College). During these years Morton affiliated with several of the local scientific and medical organizations. He became an important member of the Philadelphia Association for Medical Instruction, the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia in 1820, and the American Philosophical Society in 1828. During this period he also produced his first published works; a medical paper on the use of cornine for treatment of intermittent fevers that appeared in the Philadelphia Journal of Medical and Physical Sciences in 1826 and another in 1834 that recommended fresh air for pulmonary consumption. In 1836 Morton prepared the first American edition of John Mackintosh’s authoritative Principles of Pathology and Practice of Physic.
Outside medicine, Morton built a substantial reputation as an adept natural historian. Joseph Parrish’s assistant the naturalist and anatomist Richard Harlan, who got Morton elected to the Academy of Natural Science, directed his scientific research. His earliest research projects in the late 1820s and 1830s, are epitomized by his well-regarded study of the fossils collected by Lewis and Clark, Synopsis of the Organic Remains of the Cretaceous Group of the United States (1834). While his interests centered on the then-chic fields of geology and paleontology, he soon shifted his focus to anthropology.
In 1830 Morton began to collect human craniums, later accumulating over 1,000. He began to take a deep interest in racial science, and his groundbreaking work in craniology and craniometry proved to be the most enduring of his scientific contributions. The prominence of phrenology in Philadelphia scientific circles, reflected in the work of Charles Caldwell and others, quickened Morton's interests in the measurement of skulls as a means of identifying and comparing the intellectual capacities and "character" of the races. He was never a field anthropologist. Rather, he depended entirely upon scientific colleagues such as Marmaduke Burrough (1767-1844, APS 1833) and Ephraim George Squier, as well as merchants, missionaries, and members of the military for specimens, eventually assembling the largest collection of skulls in North America. These became the basis of his painstaking, statistical comparisons of human populations. His skull collection was eventually donated to the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia and is documented in the exhaustive Catalogue of Skulls of Man, and the Inferior Animals, in the Collection of Samuel George Morton(1840).
The first fruits of Morton's research were published as Crania Americana, or, a Comparative View of the Skulls of Various Aboriginal Nations of North and South America (1839), a work which sought to corroborate the five-fold racial division of Johann Friedrich Blumenbach (1752-1840, APS 1798). Based upon his estimates of cranial volume, Morton concluded that the American Indians from Canada to Patagonia were descended from a common stock (i.e., were monophyletic) that was clearly distinct from the races of the Old World. He argued forcefully against the theory that environment contributed to race formation. More importantly for the subsequent history of racial science, Morton claimed to have demonstrated the presence of significant differences in cranial capacity -- and therefore intelligence -- among the races, with "Mongolians" and Caucasians heading the list, and "Americans" and "Ethiopians" at the bottom of the hierarchy.
In his second major work in the field, Crania Aegyptiaca, or, Observations on Egyptian Ethnography, Derived from Anatomy, History, and the Monuments(1844), Morton took his reasoning further. Comparing skulls obtained by George R. Gliddon from archaeological sites in Egypt, he deduced that racial distinctions were as prominent 6,000 years ago as they were in 1840. The elite of Ancient Egypt, he argued, were Caucasians, and while "Negroes" were abundant, "their social position, in ancient times was the same as it now is; that of servants or slaves." In essence, Morton argued for the polygenic origins of humanity and the inexpungibility of racial distinctions.
Morton's work on craniology met with a receptive audience in much of the United States. The country’s scientific elite such as Harvard naturalist Louis Agassiz lauded its massive empirical base. The implications of his theories for human relations were endorsed avidly by pro-slavery advocates. His most zealous supporters were George R. Gliddon and the Alabama physician, Josiah Nott, who developed his own, highly elaborated polygenic theory as an apologetic for slavery. However, support for Morton's conclusions did not align easily with such sentiments. The apparent conflict of Morton's work with the theory of unitary origins presented in the book of Genesis proved unpalatable to many religiously-inclined scientists, including those who defended slavery on other grounds. Prominent among his detractors was the South Carolinian, John Bachman, a Lutheran minister and natural historian, who was no opponent of slavery. Bachman argued that the interfertility of Africans and Caucasians proved the Doctrine of the Unity of the Human Race(1850). Morton responded to such claims with an investigation into the hybridization in plants and animals that appeared in Silliman’s American Journal of Science and Arts (1847). Perhaps more importantly, he seems to have avoided addressing the social implications of his craniology.
Morton, who suffered ill health for much of his life, had an attack of pleurisy in 1848 that seriously weakened his heart and lungs. Three years later he died. It was reported that before his illness Morton had planned a work on the "Elements of Ethnology"; however, he died before he could begin the new work. Friends remarked on his modesty, courtesy and “gentleness of manner.” Morton was survived by his wife Rebecca and all of his eight children.
Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia.; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851; Bachman, John, 1790-1874; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887; Bird, Robert Montgomery, 1806-1854; Breck, Samuel, 1771-1862; Brongniart, Alexandre, 1770-1847; Buckland, William, 1784-1856; Caldwell, Charles, 1772-1853; Chapman, Nathaniel, 1780-1853; Cleaveland, Parker, 1780-1858; Combe, George, 1788-1858; Conrad, T. A., (Timothy Abbott), 1803-1877; Cooper, William, 1776-1848; Dana, James D. (James Dwight), 1813-1895; DeKay, James Ellsworth, 1792-1851; Doornik, Jacob Elisa, 1777-1837; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844; Eaton, Amos, 1776-1842; Featherstonhaugh, George William, 1780-1866; Fermine Gomez Farias; French, B. F., (Benjamin Franklin), 1799-1877; Gliddon, George R.(George Robins),1809-1857.; Gomez, Jose Justo Gomez de la Cortina, conde de la, 1799-1860; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880; Harlan, Richard, 1796-1843; Hildreth, Samuel P. (Samuel Prescott), 1783-1863; Hodgkin, Thomas, 1798-1866; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859; Kane, John K., (John Kintzing), 1795-1858; La Roche, R., (René), 1795-1872; Locke, John, 1792-1856; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875; Maclure, William, 1763-1840; Mantell, Gideon Algernon, 1790-1852; Mitchill, Samuel L., (Samuel Latham), 1764-1831; Nuttall, Thomas, 1786-1859; Peale, Rembrandt, 1778-1860; Pickering, Charles, 1805-1878; Poinsett, Joel Roberts, 1779-1851; Ravenel, Edmund, 1797-1871; Ruschenberger, W. S. W., (William Samuel Waithman), 1807-1895; Rush, William, 1756-1833; Say, Lucy Way Sistaire, 1801-1886; Say, Thomas, 1787-1834; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864; Schweinitz, Lewis David von, 1780-1834; Silliman, Benjamin, Sr., 1779-1864; Tappan, Benjamin, 1773-1857; Torrey, John, 1796-1873; Troost, Gerard, 1776-1850; Warren, John Collins, 1778-1856; Wied-Neuwied, Maximilien Alexandre Philippe, prinz von, 1782-1864; African American; Archaeology; Aymara Indians; Barbados--Description and travel--19th century; Botany; Craniology.; Craniometry; Diaries.; Eastern Woodlands Indians; Education; Egyptology.; Exploration.; General Correspondence; Geology; Indians of North America--Kentucky; Indians of North America--Massachusetts; Indians of North America--Mississippi; Indians of North America--Ohio; Indians of North America--Physical characteristics; Indians of North America--Rhode Island; Indians of North America--Tennessee; Indians of South America--Peru; Indians of South America--Physical characteristics; International Travel; Medicine; Mineralogy; Miscegenation; Natural history; Naumkeag Indians; Ornithology; Paleontology; Pentland, Joseph Barclay; Phrenology; Race; Race, race relations, racism; Science and technology; Scientific Correspondence; Sketches.; Skull.; Slavery--Barbados; Slaves, slavery, slave trade; Southeast Indians; Travel; Travel Narratives and Journals; United States Exploring Expedition (1838-1842); Watercolors
- Series I. Correspondence, 2.25 Linear feet 5 boxes, 486 items.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 consists of incoming correspondence (c. 490 letters) from many of the major scientists of the period, over two thirds of the collection dates from the 1830s, when Morton was beginning his craniological investigations in earnest, and was in full stride with his work in mineralogy and paleontology. With the exception of the letters from Doornik, Bardi, Brogniart, Société Francaise, Société géologique, Auber, and Blainville (in French), and Cisneros (in Spanish), the letters are in English.
  Morton's omnivorous interests in natural historical and medical subjects emerge through his correspondence. However, because the collection is comprised almost exclusively of in-coming letters, Morton's perspective generally must be inferred from the responses of his correspondents. His abundant correspondence with the phrenologist George Combe and with George Gliddon, Marmaduke Burrough, Gerard Troost, and James Cowles Prichard, provides particularly useful information about the development of Morton's skull collection and the evolution of his thoughts on craniometry during the late 1830s and early 1840s. Almost all of the letters by Samuel Prescott Hildreth deal with his efforts to acquire Native American skulls for Morton, as do the letters from Martin, who served as medical director for the Cherokee nation at the time of the removal, John James Audubon, who tried to acquire skulls in England, William Powell, who offered Morton the use of his large collection of Native American crania, and E. H. Abadie, who served as physician to the U.S. troops in Florida in the late 1830s. A manuscript written late in life, "Some remarks on the infrequency of mixed offspring between the European and Australian races" (1850) bears the stamp of a response to John Bachman's critique of Morton's polygenism, and can be seen as a bellwether for his never-published work, "Elements of Ethnology."
  A few items relate to Morton’s medical training. They include Joseph Parrish’s statement regarding his qualifications (1820) as well as a letter by J. Chaloner who congratulates Morton for obtaining a “license to kill and cure all over the world” (7 July 1823). A letter by G. Fitzgerald offers the playful remark that Morton must be “in the midst of [his] academic studies, surrounded by dry physics and crabbed by boring latin” (19 April 1823).
  Of interest are also the letters by William Maclure, in which he discusses a variety of topics, including his reform efforts in the United States and Mexico, where he spent the last years of his life. Maclure also notes that he lost large sums of money in Owen’s failed community of New Harmony. On many occasions, Maclure writes about educational matters. He frequently identifies an inequality in property and knowledge as the cause of all evil (27 December 1836), and on more than one occasion he describes his attempts to bring “knowledge” to Mexico, “this half barbarous country” (3 April 1830). The letters by Marmaduke Burrough frequently contain information about Maclure, including Maclure’s opposition to the Academy of Natural Sciences’ plan to tear down its hall and Maclure’s intention to bequeath his fortune and collection to the Academy. Burrough’s letters also shed some light on life in South America during the 1830s. In one letter, for example, Burrough admits his “apprehension for the security of my person against the use of fire arms unless my shutters are closed” (19 November 1836).
  The letters by Thomas Hodgkins, a physician and evidently an old acquaintance of Morton, deal mostly with Hodgkin’s plans to bring several young Native American men to England for their education. Benjamin Silliman’s letters relate primarily with Morton’s contributions to his Journal as well as notes about fellow scientists. Also of interest is an angry letter by Dr. Harlan which accuses Morton of “illegitimate and ungentlemanly interference” with his patients (9 December 1831).
  More typical of the collection, however, are the numerous letters on other natural historical subjects, ranging from botany and ornithology to geology. Morton's work in mineralogy and paleontology, in particular, is an important subject of his correspondence with Parker Cleaveland, Edward Hitchcock, Maclure, Benjamin Silliman, Gideon Mantell, and William Cooper. In one letter, John Kirk Townshend reports that a band of Iroquois had seen an animal that matched the description of “the supposed extinct Mastodon” (12 April 1836). Of particular interest is Charles Pickering’s detailed (and confidential) discussion of his observation that species are “always adapted by Nature” (8 August 1840).
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Dec. 20, 1819; 8" x 9 3/4"; Bigsby, John J. (John Jeremiah), 1792-1881
    Quebec, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Has been sick. Is introducing Dr. A. Fyfe. Refers to excursions.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, April 16, 1820; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia
    Philadelphia, A.L.S: Franklin Bache, Recg. secretary. 1p. and add. Elected member.
  - Statement regarding qualifications of Samuel George Morton, April 29, 1820; 8" x 10"; Parrish, Joseph, 1779-1840
    Philadelphia, A.D.S. 1p. Testifies to his medical qualifications.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, Dec. 30, 1820; 7 1/4" x 9"; Lawson, John
    A.L.S. 3p. and add. Thanks for minerals. Discusses mineralogy.
  - Letter to Samuel [George] Morton, Jan. 26, 1822; 7 1/4" x 9 1/4"; Fitzgerald, G.
    Clonmel, A.L.S. 3p. and add.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, June 30, 1822; 7 1/4" x 9 1/2"; Hodgkin, Thomas, 1798-1866
    Jardin du Roi, A.L.S. 4p. add. Regarding politics, shipment of speciments.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, April 13, 1823; 7 1/2" x 9"; Fitzgerald, G.
    Clonmel, A.L.S. 4p. add. Friendly letter, asks about his studies, reporting news from home.
  - Letter to Samuel [George] Morton, July 7, 1823; 7 1/4" x 9"; Chaloner, J.
    Clonmel, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Friendly letter, congratulations to medical license. Refers to his own writings.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, Dec., 1823; 8" x 10"; Marshall, B. A.
    A.L.S. 4p. add. Reagrding his poetry, plans to visit France. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, July 30, 1824; 4 1/2" x 7 1/4"; Alison, William Pulteney, 1790-1859
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Sorry to hear he is sick and will not attend [university] event.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Dec. 17, 1824; 8" x 10"; Hodgkin, Thomas, 1798-1866
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Regarding treatment of Native Americans. Hopes to bring two Indians to study in Europe. Freeman Guide 1435.
  - Letter to John Norton, Dec. 17, 1824; 7 1/4" x 9"; Hodgkin, Thomas, 1798-1866
    A.L.S. 4p.add. "Copy." Relates to letter to Morton of same date.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, June 2, 1825; 8" x 10"; Hodgkin, Thomas, 1798-1866
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, July 20, 1825; 7 1/4" x 12"; Fitzgerald, G.
    Clonmel, A.L.S. 4p. add. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, July 28, 1825; 8" x 9 3/4"; Hodgkin, Thomas, 1798-1866
    London, A.L.S. 4p.add. Regarding his plan to bring young Indians to Europe for education. Freeman Guide 1436.
  - Letter to samuel George Morton, April 10, 1826; 6" x 7 3/4"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
    New Harmony, Ind., A.L.S. 2p. and add. Re. Agricultural Society. Purchase of New Jerusalem church.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Dec. 8, 1826; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Lyceum of Natural History (New York)